<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Charles Martin</title><subtitle>Charles Martin is a computer scientist and musician specialising in music technology, creative AI, and human-computer interaction.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2008-08-25-theremin-to-midi-control-program-in-pd" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2008-08-25-theremin-to-midi-control-program-in-pd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2008-08-25-theremin-to-midi-control-program-in-pd"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/blogger/ThereminController.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><em>Update:</em> throughout 2008 and 2009 I used these techniques with the vibraphone in my piece “Duet for Vibraphone and Computer”</p>

<p>Over the weekend I wrote a simple program in Pd that analyses an audio input and then uses pitch and amplitude information to output a midi control value.</p>

<p>My idea was to use my little theremin as the audio input and send the midi data to an internal midi bus which is received by Ableton Live for controlling parameters of some effects. Since the theremin has such a simple sound the pitch and amplitude analysis works extremely well. To achieve this feat I use the excellent fiddle~ object (written by Miller Puckette) and… well not much else really! A few * and + objects adjust the output values so that they are sensibly distributed between 0-127.</p>

<p>Here’s the code (or just copy from the picture!):</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>#N canvas 738 31 442 441 10;
#X obj 88 21 adc~ 1;
#X obj 88 44 *~ 1;
#X obj 29 91 *~;
#X obj 59 91 tgl 15 0 empty empty empty 17 7 0 10 -262144 -1 -1 0 1;
#X obj 29 114 dac~ 1;
#X text 9 146 Audio Output!;
#X obj 147 114 unpack;
#X obj 188 177 moses 1;
#X floatatom 219 214 5 0 0 0 Note - -;
#X floatatom 109 214 5 0 0 0 Amplitude - -;
#X obj 117 83 fiddle~ 1024;
#X obj 50 411 ctlout 14;
#X obj 195 411 ctlout 15;
#X obj 222 303 tgl 15 0 empty on empty 17 7 0 10 -262144 -1 -1 1 1;
#X obj 192 303 *;
#X obj 54 245 *;
#X obj 54 268 +;
#X floatatom 91 245 5 0 100 0 - ampmult -;
#X floatatom 91 265 5 -127 127 0 - ampshift -;
#X obj 190 240 *;
#X obj 190 263 +;
#X floatatom 227 242 5 0 100 0 - pitchmult -;
#X floatatom 227 265 5 0 0 0 - pitchshift -;
#X obj 232 368 tgl 15 0 empty on empty 17 7 0 10 -262144 -1 -1 1 1;
#X obj 201 368 *;
#X floatatom 212 328 5 0 0 0 - - -;
#X obj 84 303 tgl 15 0 empty on empty 17 7 0 10 -262144 -1 -1 1 1;
#X obj 54 303 *;
#X obj 94 368 tgl 15 0 empty on empty 17 7 0 10 -262144 -1 -1 1 1;
#X obj 63 368 *;
#X floatatom 74 328 5 0 0 0 - - -;
#X text 147 14 Theremin Controller;
#X obj 303 162 loadbang;
#X msg 302 184 \; pitchmult 2 \; pitchshift -80 \; ampmult 1 \; ampshift
20 \;;
#X obj 302 253 loadbang;
#X obj 303 275 s on;
#X text 147 34 Output midi controller data;
#X text 146 49 from pitch and amplitude input.;
#X text 292 402 Charles Martin;
#X text 293 414 25/08/08;
#X text 301 145 Default Settings;
#X connect 0 0 1 0;
#X connect 1 0 2 0;
#X connect 1 0 10 0;
#X connect 2 0 4 0;
#X connect 3 0 2 1;
#X connect 6 0 7 0;
#X connect 6 1 9 0;
#X connect 7 1 8 0;
#X connect 8 0 19 0;
#X connect 9 0 15 0;
#X connect 10 2 6 0;
#X connect 13 0 14 1;
#X connect 14 0 25 0;
#X connect 15 0 16 0;
#X connect 16 0 27 0;
#X connect 17 0 15 1;
#X connect 18 0 16 1;
#X connect 19 0 20 0;
#X connect 20 0 14 0;
#X connect 21 0 19 1;
#X connect 22 0 20 1;
#X connect 23 0 24 1;
#X connect 24 0 12 0;
#X connect 25 0 24 0;
#X connect 26 0 27 1;
#X connect 27 0 30 0;
#X connect 28 0 29 1;
#X connect 29 0 11 0;
#X connect 30 0 29 0;
#X connect 32 0 33 0;
#X connect 34 0 35 0;
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>To check it out, copy and paste the code into a text editor, save it as a .pd file, then open in Pd! Click the little toggle boxes to first to view the data and then to send it to the midi output. This way you can shut off output of one parameter while you have Live (for example) learn the assignment.</p>

<p><strong>Update:</strong> The program was a little bit wrong. Fixed now! Hello internet!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2009-06-04-sounding-the-glassworks" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2009-06-04-sounding-the-glassworks</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2009-06-04-sounding-the-glassworks"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/blogger/fitters-workshop-striking.jpg" alt="Source: [CIMF Photos](http://www.flickr.com/people/cimfphotos/)" /></p>

<!-- [![](http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3584/3518272361_f14789550a_m.jpg)](http://www.flickr.com/photos/cimfphotos/3518272361/) -->

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/cimfphotos/3518272361/">Charles at “Sounding the Glassworks”</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2011-05-13-crowdfunding-musical-projects" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2011-05-13-crowdfunding-musical-projects</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2011-05-13-crowdfunding-musical-projects"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been thinking a bit about “crowd funding” recently since some good friends were successful in using Kickstarter to fund their commissioning project for percussion music. Kickstarter is for US residents only but I see that there’s an similar product called <a href="http://www.pozible.com.au/">Pozible</a> available for Australians.</p>

<p>Is there something “new” going on in crowd funding? I guess the new thing is the “all or nothing” approach, where Kickstarter or whatever website holds on to your backer’s money until the project has 100% of the required funding, otherwise it is returned after the call is over. The idea being that the entrepreneurs are never in the position of doing a project with only 80% of the funding (not so much fun…)  and the backers don’t see their money going into projects that fail through a lack of funds.</p>

<p>The other “new” thing I guess is that the websites have all the right social media hooks so that entrepreneurs can make their projects visible to all their friends on Facebook.</p>

<p>Is this useful for people like me? Can it help fund crazy performance/installations and pay me to work on them?</p>

<p>Most of the kickstarter projects that I see on the blogs area actually presales of things…. design books, arduino shields, touch screen writing doodads and CDs. In many of these cases they’re actually only funding the LAST stage of the project, i.e. the doodad has already been conceived, designed and prototyped, they’ve already been out to the doodad factory and decided that they need to sell 5000 doodads to do a production run, so they just need to go ahead and do that in their Kickstarter, and everyone who backs them for the price a doodad will get one after they’re produced.</p>

<p>Craigmod wrote a great <a href="http://craigmod.com/journal/kickstartup/">analysis</a> of his Kickstarter experience which goes exactly like this.</p>

<p>In all of these presale cases there’s actually multiple steps for the whole and usually in the Kickstarter projects the cost of the early steps was “free”, i.e. somebody gave up all there free time to make it happen. This is probably not a recipe for a sustainable business unless the final stage makes a LOT of money, i.e. enough to pay for all the time you gave away at the start. For making doodads, maybe it is if your doodad can go into further production after the initial run. For making contemporary art it’s probably not.</p>

<hr />

<p>Usually my projects go something like this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>(creative development, research) —&gt; development —&gt; production —&gt; performance</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think that crowd-funding works best for the final stage, where you can offer something like a CD or a concert ticket to the backers. In general, it’s easier to convince backers when there’s a clear line to a tangible outcome. Asking someone to give me money to develop a work that might be produced and performed later down the track is always going to be a hard sell.</p>

<p>And this is exactly what the design book writers, doodad makers and CD recorders know intuitively and implement in their calls for funding.</p>

<hr />

<p>Craigmod makes a point that I think is interesting: “people don’t mind paying $50 or more for a project they love”</p>

<p>Since all the backers above $65 received a copy of the design book Craigmod was printing, I’m not very surprised about this. $65 is inexpensive for a beautifully produced book and obviously people don’t mind spending $50 or more on it, these are the same people who love and buy all those other crazy expensive design books.</p>

<p>I think the real lesson is (common sense alert…) “the thing you’re preselling should be sold for around it’s normal value” or probably a little bit cheaper, since the whole idea is asking people to PRE pay for it.</p>

<p>Anyway, some thoughts, I’ll elaborate later on.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2011-05-15-how-fitting-is-fitters-workshop" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2011-05-15-how-fitting-is-fitters-workshop</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2011-05-15-how-fitting-is-fitters-workshop"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://farm4.static.flickr.com/3577/3496432939_e5433f5409.jpg" alt="Fitter's Workshop" /></p>

<p>A bit of controversy on the blargs recently about “Fitter’s Workshop”, an antique building in Canberra (the controversy being whether the ACT Government should turn it into a facility for printmakers or into a concert venue).  I’ve been out of town for a while, so I don’t know all the details of the latest flare up, but I’m going to share the thoughts that I’ve had since last year.</p>

<p>Basically I’m not sure that Fitter’s Workshop is all that fitting as a concert venue anyway.   I’ve had a number of extremely rewarding concert experiences there and it’s true it has an beautiful resonant acoustic  (great for performances of choral and brass works with lots of long mellifluous tones). But there are downsides from a concert perspective. It has no chairs, stage or lights, so all of these things have to be trucked in at great effort and expense. It’s difficult to load instruments and equipment since there’s no road connected to the dock at the back. The HUGE windows mean that it’s bright and uncomfortable to read music or see instruments during the day (especially in winter when the sun is low) and freezing cold at night. There’s no box office, or easy access to toilets or kitchens for catering. There’s not much within walking distance to grab dinner before or after a concert (except the lovely glassworks café).</p>

<p>All of these problems would need to be addressed permanently in order to make it a more “professional” concert venue.</p>

<p>Of course, these problems can be overcome in an ad hoc way for some projects - the CIMF achieves great results by having concert series (economy of scale), and harnessing hard work of dedicated performers and organisers around Canberra to lug all of the equipment in and make the whole show happen (I was proud to be involved in 2009 and 2010 and carried many chairs and instruments).</p>

<p>But I think that concert venues and music festivals are different beasts. Supposing Fitter’s Workshop became a pro venue, equivalent in support infrastructure to Llewellyn hall or the Street Theatre, the cost of hiring it would probably make it LESS desirable to festivals like CIMF. Plus, it would be in competition to the other excellent venues across the water and many other venues with real permanent concert facilities around town.</p>

<p>Personally, I wouldn’t hire the Fitter’s Workshop for the kind of one-off or short run performances I organise. The acoustic is all wrong for me and the lack of infrastructure is too hard and expensive for me to overcome. For me, the Fitter’s Workshop doesn’t fit at all.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2011-05-28-speaker-noise-instrument" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2011-05-28-speaker-noise-instrument</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2011-05-28-speaker-noise-instrument"><![CDATA[<p>I went to Nicholas Collins’ “hardware hacking” workshop at NIME2011. It was SO FUN.</p>

<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/346998758">video</a></p>

<iframe style="display:block; margin:0 auto;" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/346998758" width="500" height="281" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2012-10-08-nattmusik-with-ensemble-evolution" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2012-10-08-nattmusik-with-ensemble-evolution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2012-10-08-nattmusik-with-ensemble-evolution"><![CDATA[<p>In June 2012, Ensemble Evolution put together a “farewell” tour in Northern Sweden to celebrate everything the area had given to us and enjoy the midnight sun and amazing natural environment.</p>

<p>We performed concerts at Storforsen Hotel’s Chapel, Piteå Badhusparken, Luleå’s “Lillan” Theatre and the iconic <a href="http://www.treehotel.se">Treehotel</a> at Harads. Ensemble Evolution was joined by clarinetist, Angela Occhionero, an old friend of Maria’s from the US and our longtime collaborator, Anna K. Larson (interactive vocalist). Together we performed repertoire that we had put together over our two years in residence in Piteå and new works commissioned by Treehotel for each of their tree house suites.</p>

<!-- https://youtu.be/BLl5OwuKs58 -->

<style>.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }</style>
<div class="embed-container"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BLl5OwuKs58" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>

<p>Two of my favourite performances are embedded here, Jacob and myself playing one of my tunes “Footprints in Snow” at Storforsen above and Ensemble Evolution playing our “Solstormen” suite at Badhusparken below.</p>

<!-- https://youtu.be/PHZwQEI8Caw -->

<style>.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }</style>
<div class="embed-container"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/PHZwQEI8Caw" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>

<p>Every performance was recorded, so there’s too much material to post it all here, but everything is on youtube in <a href="http://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLnRoOVbpGXfZaRKZACoUu-uJFDnXCo9Qa&amp;feature=addto">this playlist</a>!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2012-10-11-lunchbox-concert-at-the-anu-school-of-music" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2012-10-11-lunchbox-concert-at-the-anu-school-of-music</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2012-10-11-lunchbox-concert-at-the-anu-school-of-music"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/squarespace_images/2012-10-11-LunchboxConcertANU.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I played a fun concert today with Gary France at the ANU School of Music. We played Maria Schnieder’s “The Pretty Road” as a duo to open a Lunchbox Concert with lots of his students. It was really great to see that there are great things still happening over at the School of Music and lots of cool things to come!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2012-10-28-exporting-auxiliary-channels-in-logic" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2012-10-28-exporting-auxiliary-channels-in-logic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2012-10-28-exporting-auxiliary-channels-in-logic"><![CDATA[<p>A <a href="http://support.apple.com/kb/HT3650?viewlocale=en_US&amp;locale=en_US#">good tip from Apple Support</a> on how to export the sound of auxiliary channel strips in Logic when doing an “export all tracks”</p>

<p>The trick is to select the channel strips then go “Option -&gt; Create Arrange Tracks for Selected Channel Strips”, then to put short empty regions in each track.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2013-02-13-new-release-sounds-from-the-treetops" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2013-02-13-new-release-sounds-from-the-treetops</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2013-02-13-new-release-sounds-from-the-treetops"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/squarespace_images/2013-02-13-SoundsFromTheTreetopsCDFront.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Ensemble Evolution’s new album “Sounds from the Treetops” has just gone live on Bandcamp! The album features music by all three of us, including two tracks (Planks and Mirror Cube) by me!</p>

<p>I’m super excited - this album was recorded in Sweden in just two days after a hectic three weeks writing and rehearsing the music and premiering the works on our tour to the Treehotel at Harads, Northern Sweden. After recording it it took us four months of on and off work to choose the takes and for me to do some preliminary mixing before sending it to Sebastian Lönberg, our mastering engineer and now finally it’s out!</p>

<p>It’s free to stream online, so press play below and if you like what you hear, consider buying a digital copy and helping to support our music making!</p>

<p><a href="http://ensembleevolution.bandcamp.com/album/sounds-from-the-treetops">Sounds from the Treetops by Ensemble Evolution</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html"></title><link href="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2013-04-29-sounds-from-the-treetops-cd-available" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="" /><published>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T10:49:37+00:00</updated><id>https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2013-04-29-sounds-from-the-treetops-cd-available</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://charlesmartin.au/blog/2024/07/27/2013-04-29-sounds-from-the-treetops-cd-available"><![CDATA[<p>Ensemble Evolution’s first album, “Sounds from the Treetops” is now available as a REAL CD over on <a href="http://ensembleevolution.bandcamp.com/album/sounds-from-the-treetops">Bandcamp!</a></p>

<p>The CD features a lightweight sleeve with cover art by Piteå’s Mozarts Ögonbryn Design Studio - and every CD purchase includes the digital version and our special liner notes with a photo-essay of our concert at the Treehotel! <a href="http://ensembleevolution.bandcamp.com/album/sounds-from-the-treetops">Go check it out on Bandcamp.</a></p>

<p><a href="http://ensembleevolution.bandcamp.com/album/sounds-from-the-treetops">Sounds from the Treetops by Ensemble Evolution</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>